A Guide to the Woman’s Club of Fairfax Collection, 1956-2004
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Woman’s Club of Fairfax Collection, 1956-2004
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 05-52
3.0 linear feet
The Woman’s Club of Fairfax Collection consists of 3.0 linear feet and spans the years 1956-2004 and contains newsletters, event programs, newspaper clippings, photographs, reports, certificates, and scrapbooks of photos, newspaper clippings, and event programs.
Woman’s Club of Fairfax
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Donated by the Woman’s Club of Fairfax at an unknown date
Historical and Biographical Information
The Woman’s Club of Fairfax (WCF) was founded in 1956 and chartered under the General Federation of Women’s Clubs (GFWC). Throughout its existence, the club has provided service to the Fairfax community through volunteer activities and financial support. WCF created and maintains the Ford House Exhibit in the Ford Building in the City of Fairfax, VA and contributes volunteer services and financial support to the preservation and restoration of Fairfax historical properties, such as the Ratcliffe-Allison-Pozer House, built by the City of Fairfax’s founder Richard Ratcliffe and formerly known as Earp’s Ordinary and the Ratcliffe-Allison House. Each year, WCF grants an achievement scholarship to a local high school senior; designs, purchases, and sells a Fairfax commemorative Christmas ornament; and contributes funds and volunteer services to Fairfax cultural and civic events such as the Independence Day celebration and Chocolate Lovers Festival. The club regularly sponsors fundraising activities such as fashion shows, yard sales, and bake sales to support local, national, and international charities and causes, and hosts a number of social activities for its members. The club’s signature event was a popular annual antiques show, held from 1957-1972.
Scope and Content
The Woman’s Club of Fairfax Collection consists of 3.0 linear feet and spans the years 1956-2004 and contains newsletters, event programs, newspaper clippings, photographs, reports, certificates, and scrapbooks of photos, newspaper clippings, and event programs. Subjects include the history and events of the Woman’s Club of Fairfax and the Ford Building and Ratcliffe-Allison-Pozer House.
Series 1: Administrative Papers, 1963-2000
This series contains year books of the Woman’s Club of Fairfax featuring bylaws and members; programs and invitations from events hosted by Virginia Federation of Women’s Clubs, Historic Fairfax City, Inc., the City of Fairfax, and Fairfax County; treasurer’s reports; General Federation Clubwoman and The Virginia Club Woman magazines; a receipt from a luncheon at the Red Fox Tavern; a program from the 1984 Olympic Torch Rally; a summary and brochure of the history of the club; and reports of the club’s Community Improvement Programs.
Series 2: Newsletters, 1969-2004
This series includes newsletters of the Woman’s Club of Fairfax, many including minutes of meetings of the club’s Executive Board.
Series 3: Certificates of Recognition, 1956-2003
This series includes certificates of membership, recognition, and achievement issued to the Woman’s Club of Fairfax or individual club members from the Virginia Federation of Women’s Clubs, General Federation of Women’s Clubs, City of Fairfax, Northern Virginia Training Center, Congressman Thomas M. Davis, Historic Fairfax City, Inc., and Kidney Foundation of the National Capital Area.
Series 4: Scrapbooks, 1956-2004
This series includes seven scrapbooks compiled since 1956, the founding year of the Woman’s Club of Fairfax, through 1998. The scrapbooks contain newspaper clippings related to the club or its members, programs from club events, and photographs from club events. One of the scrapbooks is dedicated to programs, photographs, and newspaper clippings for the club’s annual antique shows from 1957-1961. Also included are loose scrapbook materials for more recent years, 2000-2004, and undated photographs and negatives.
This series also includes a binder of clippings from local newspapers and newsletters saved by the Woman’s Club of Fairfax. Clippings include articles on events hosted, sponsored, or supported by the club; club participation in community events and fundraising efforts; participation of individual club members in local events; death notices for club members; appointment of club officers; club and member awards; and award of the club’s annual scholarship. The binder of news clippings also includes several related photographs and event programs.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
None
Index Terms
Fairfax (Va.) - History; Ford Building (Fairfax, Va.); Ratcliffe-Allison-Pozer House (Fairfax, Va.); Woman’s Club of Fairfax (Fairfax, Va.)
Container List
- Series 1: Administrative Papers, 1963-2000
  - Year Books, 1963-1969, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Receipt from Red Fox Tavern, 17 May 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General Federation Clubwoman; The Virginia Club Woman, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Program from Olympic Torch Rally,, May 15, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Event Invitations and Programs (non-WCF), 1976-1982, 1976-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Event Invitations and Programs (non-WCF), 1983-2001, 1983-2001 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Treasurer’s Reports, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - History of Woman’s Club of Fairfax, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Ford House Exhibit: A Community Improvement Program, 1997-1998 (original), 1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Busy Bees: A Community Improvement Program, July 1998 - June 2000 (original), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Busy Bees: A Community Improvement Program, July 1998 - June 2000 (photocopy), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series 2: Newsletters, 1969-2004
  - Newsletters, June 1969-December 1976, 1969-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters, February 1977-December 1981, 1977-1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters, May 1983-December 1985, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters, February 1986-December 1991, 1986-1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Newsletters, February 1992-June 2004, 1992-2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series 3: Certificates of Recognition, 1956-2003
  - Certificates of Recognition, 1956-2003 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Certificates of Recognition, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Binder, Certificates of Recognition, 1956-2000 (Box 3)
- Series 4: Scrapbooks, 1956-2004
  - Loose Scrapbook Materials, 2000-2004, 2000-2004 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified Event Photographs and Negatives, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook, 1956-1961, 1956-1961 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook, Antique Shows, 1957-1961, 1957-1961 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1961-1966, 1961-1966 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1961-1988, 1961-1988 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1989-1995, 1989-1995 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1996, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1997-1998, 1997-1998 (Box 4)
  - Binder, Newspaper and Newsletter Clippings, 1957-2000 (Box 4)